<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: unicode | Hi, I’m Yang Peng]]></title>
  <link href="http://yeangpeng.tech/blog/categories/unicode/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://yeangpeng.tech/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-18T15:43:59+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://yeangpeng.tech/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Yang Peng]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[me@yangpeng.tech]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HDF5 on Windows: UTF-8 filenames support]]></title>
    <link href="http://yeangpeng.tech/blog/2014/11/07/hdf5-on-windows-utf-8-filenames-support/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-07T02:10:35+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://yeangpeng.tech/blog/2014/11/07/hdf5-on-windows-utf-8-filenames-support</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In a previous <a href="http://tschoonj.github.io/blog/2014/01/29/building-a-64-bit-version-of-hdf5-with-mingw-w64/">post</a>, I have detailed my efforts in getting HDF5 compiled on Windows 64-bit using the MinGW-w64 compiler, which is currently (still) unsupported by the HDF5 developers. Now, I am reporting on yet another problem I encountered with HDF5 on Windows, that is blatantly being ignored by the developers: UTF-8 filename support.</p>

<p>This was brought to my attention by a Japanese user of my software package <a href="http://github.com/tschoonj/xmimsim">XMI-MSIM</a>, who ran into trouble running the program when logged in with a username consisting of Japanese characters. The problem could be traced back to an HDF5 file that has to be opened, which is located in a subdirectory of the user&rsquo;s homedirectory. After investigating the HDF5 code, it became quite clear that this issue is caused by the internal use of the <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/z0kc8e3z.aspx"><code>_open</code> function</a>, which is known not to support the Unicode UTF-8 characterset, necessary to represent the Japanese characters. The HDF5 website confirmed this issue with the following statement:</p>

<!--more-->


<p><blockquote><p>Linux, Unix, and similar systems generally handle UTF-8 encodings in correct and predictable ways. There is an apparent consensus in the Linux community that &ldquo;UTF-8 is just the right way to go.&rdquo;<br/>Mac OS systems generally handle UTF-8 encodings correctly.</p></p><p><p>Windows systems use a different Unicode encoding, UCS-2 (discussed in this UTF-16 article) at the system level. Within an HDF5 file and application on a Windows system, UTF-8 encoding should work correctly and as expected. Problems may arise, however, when that UTF-8 encoding is exposed directly to the Windows system. For example:</p></p><p><p>File open and close calls on files with UTF-8 encoded names are likely to fail as the HDF5 open and close operations interact directly with the Windows file system interface.<br/>Anytime an HDF5 command-line utility (h5ls or h5dump, for example) emits text output, the Windows system must interpret the character encodings. If that output is UTF-8 encoded, Windows will correctly interpret only those characters in the ASCII subset of UTF-8.</p><footer><strong>HDF5 documentation <a href="http://www.hdfgroup.org/HDF5/doc/Advanced/UsingUnicode/">http://www.hdfgroup.org/HDF5/doc/Advanced/UsingUnicode/</a></strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>So basically I was stuck here since there is no way to convert a filename in UTF-8 encoding to the UCS encoding that was expected by <code>_open</code>. <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/23285759/fopen-file-name-with-utf8-string-in-windows">A solution</a> which would have converted the filename to the corresponding short form (8 character filename with 3 character extension) using <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/aa364989%28v=vs.85%29.aspx"><code>GetShortPathName</code></a> seemed like a very ugly hack and decided not to pursue it. Instead I opted to hack the HDF5 code myself and replace all instances of <code>_open</code> with its wide char counterparts, that could be fed the UTF-8 filenames after converting them with <a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/windows/desktop/dd319072.aspx"><code>MultiByteToWideChar</code></a>.</p>

<p>Fortunately, it turned out that I was not the first one who ran into this situation and found a better solution on the <a href="http://mail.lists.hdfgroup.org/pipermail/hdf-forum_lists.hdfgroup.org/2014-August/007988.html">HDF5 forums</a>. Essentially the solution consists of redefining the <code>HDopen</code> macro from <code>_open</code> to a function of our own that converts our filename in UTF-8 encoding to the corresponding wide char representation and feed it to <code>_wopen</code>. Since we are compiling with MinGW-w64, some other modifications were necessary (the original solution relied on CMake): the src/Makefile.am file was modified in order to compile also the H5FDwindows.c and H5FDwindows.h, the latter being added to the public headers. After running <code>autoreconf -i -f</code> (I had to downgrade the required autoconf version in configure.ac for this to work, but this didn&rsquo;t create any problems), and running the configure script, I modified the src/H5pubconf.h file according to my <a href="http://tschoonj.github.io/blog/2014/01/29/building-a-64-bit-version-of-hdf5-with-mingw-w64/">earlier post</a>, but had to add one more line:</p>

<pre><code class="c ">//fixes first problem
#ifndef H5_HAVE_WIN32_API
#ifdef WIN32 /* defined for all windows systems */
#define H5_HAVE_WIN32_API 1
#endif
#endif

#ifndef H5_HAVE_MINGW
#ifdef __MINGW32__ /*defined for all MinGW compilers */
#define H5_HAVE_MINGW 1
//additional line necessary for UTF-8 build to succeed
#define H5_HAVE_WINDOWS 1
#endif
#endif

//fixes second problem
#define H5_BUILT_AS_DYNAMIC_LIB 1
</code></pre>

<p>Keep in mind that this file is recreated after running configure, so these modifications will have to be repeated!!!</p>

<p>This solution is not pretty, and it will have to be repeated every time you compile a new version of HDF5. Ideally, the HDF5 developers would implement a solution based on this hack, which would bring it in line with most other open-source projects that assume UTF-8 filenames on all platforms. I doubt this will happen anytime soon though, since the original solution posted on the HDF5 forums has not been commented on by any of the developers&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
